Guide to the Walter Metzger American Association of University Professors Records of Academic Freedom and Tenure, 1888-2009 MS2369
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
The Walter Metzger American Association of University Professors Records of Academic Freedom and Tenure
1888-2009
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MS2369
52 Linear Feet 102 boxes
This collection contains correspondence, articles, speeches, biographical data, and subject and research files. These materials represent the personal papers of Walter Metzger, the materials he created and collected as an Academic Freedom scholar and valued member of the American Association of University Professors. The materials date from 1888-2009.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Arrangement
Organized into 6 series: History of American Association of University Professors, AAUP Academic Freedom and Tenure, Drafts and Published Materials, Higher Education and Professionalism, Correspondence, and Card Catalogues.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Gillian Metzger, 2017 September 6. (Acc2017.067)
Biographical / Historical
Walter P. Metzger (1922- 2016) was a historian and professor who led the American Association of University Professors towards better outlining and understanding the concept of Academic Freedom in higher education. After teaching and receiving his PhD from University of Iowa in 1950, he went on to continue his career at Columbia University in their history department, lecturing on 20th century U.S history. In 1955, Metzger co-authored the book "The Development of Academic Freedom in the United States" with Richard Hofstadter, which became the authoritative account of the history of academic freedom from colonial times until World War I. By the next year, in response to McCarthyism attack on academic freedom, General Secretary of the American Association of University Professors, Ralph F. Fuchs, invited Metzger to chair Committee H, a committee that centered on the History of the Association. Thus, a series of articles on AAUP history and the academic profession popularized the cultivation of academic freedom and tenure across the U.S. In 1958, he was appointed to Committee A, on Academic Freedom and Tenure, for which he continued his membership until retirement in 1985; yet, he still continued to act as a senior consultant until 2000. Within his 43 year tenure at Columbia University, he was the recipient of the 1990 Mark Van Doren Prize for teaching and was recognized as the official historian of AAUP, for which he dedicated his entire professional life to the organization with his contributions to Committee A on Academic Freedom and Tenure and his research on the history of higher education and academic freedom.
Scope and Contents
The materials within the collection provide us with Walter Metzgers research of the role and rights of tenured professors in higher education. This collection consists of AAUP policies, correspondence, case files, journal articles, newspaper clippings, academic publications, magazines, educational pamphlets, catalogue cards, notes, and committee minutes between 1820 and 2009.
- History of American Association of University Professors, 1910-1993; Series 1
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains research materials surrounding the founding of American Association of University Professors and how they developed during World War I, the 1920s and the Great Depression. These files are dated from 1910-1993.
  Arrangement
  This series was organized into 3 subseries: Founding of AAUP, World War I, and the 20s and the Depression.
  - Founding of AAUP, 1913-1989; Series 1 Subseries 1
    This subseries contains the initial cases, committees, membership logs, reports, and early files of the AAUP. These files are dated from 1913-1989.
    This subseries is arranged by subject.
    - Bryn Mawr Case, 1915; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Bryn Mawr Case, 1915; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Bibliography- Archives- Universities, 1961; Series 1 Sub series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Bibliography- Archives- Universities, 1933-1976; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Call From Johns Hopkins University and Responses, 1913; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Colorado- Brewster, 1915; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Committee on History of Association, 1957-1971; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Committee on History of Association, 1957-1989; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Documents: List of Officers, 1915-1942; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Documents: Bulletin, November 13, 1933; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Dartmouth- Oklahoma, A&M (Chambliss), June 1915- September 1915; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Documents: Self- Survey, 1965-1991; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Documents: AAUP Constitutions, 1934-1956; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Founding of AAUP, 1984-1989; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - AAUP in Ohio, 1974; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Lovejoy Files: Committee P, 1919; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Lovejoy Files: Committee P, 1919; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Lovejoy Files: Committee P, 1919; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Early Membership, 1915-1957; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Marietta Case (Morse), 1913-1914; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Montana Case, 1915-1917; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Reports, 1915-1917; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - On the Founding- Notes, Texts, Correspondence, 1961-1969; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Professional Response to AAUP, 1913-1914; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Williard Fischer, 1913-1979; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - World War I, 1910-1993; Series 1 Subseries 2
    This subseries contains case files, AAUP policies, and research materials concerning the function of AAUP during World War I at various universities. These files are dated from 1910-1993.
    - AAUP Policy: 1918 Statement, Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - World War One: Cases, 1918-1993; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Special- Lovejoy, 1917-1927; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Beard Resignation, 1917; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Cattell Dismissal, 1917; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Cattell Dismissal, 1917; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Columbia Under Butler, 1910-1972; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Students at Columbia WWI, 1976; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Committee A- Columbia University- Cattell, J. McKeen, 1918-1923; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Academia in WWI, 1918-1976; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Spingarn- Columbia, 1970-1973; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Special- Lovejoy on Cattell Dismissal, 1919-1933; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Colorado College, July 9,1917; Series 1 Sub series 2 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - The 1920s and the Depression, 1917-1973; Series 2 Subseries 3
    This subseries contains case files, AAUP policies, and research materials concerning the function of AAUP during World War I at various universities. These files are dated from 1917-1973.
    - Committee A- Lovejoy Files: Washburn College, Kirkpatrick, 1917-1921; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Material on Hedding College Case: Barnhart, Schrock and Gilmer, 1920; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Committee F: Rulings, 1917-1928; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Lovejoy Miscellaneous, 1922-1929; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Lovejoy Files: Controversy Over Bulletin, 1922-1927; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Summaries of Committee A Work, 1926-1949; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Lovejoy File: Bethany College, 1919-1920; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Special: Public Responses to AAUP, undated; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Special: AAUP Membership, 1955; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Special: AAUP Chapter, 1933-1973; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Academe in Great Depression, undated; Series 1 Subseries 3 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- AAUP Academic Freedom and Tenure, 1888-2009; Series 2
  This series contains research materials concerning the development of Academic Freedom and Tenure, Academic Freedom and Tenure Cases, Committee papers and policies. These files are dated from 1888-2009.
  This series was organized into 3 subseries: Academic Freedom and Tenure, Academic Freedom Cases, and AAUP Committees and Committee Policies.
  - Academic Freedom and Tenure, 1888-2005; Series 2 Subseries 1
    This subseries contains early case files, research, and publications concerning the growth of Academic Freedom and Tenure. These files are dated from 1913- 1989.
    - Theory of Academic Freedom: Historical, 1915-1963; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Academic Freedom- Medieval Sources, undated; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - German Spokesmen for Academic Freedom, undated; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - German Universities- Organization, History, 1963-1965; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Impact of German University, 1888-1953; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Antebellum College, 1829-1956; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Academic Freedom: Cases of 1890s- Business Control, 1886-1972; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Academic Freedom and Communist Issue, 1949-1963; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - AAUP and IRBs, 1981; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Current Committee A, 1993-1999; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Academic Freedom: Current Issues and Definitions, 1953-1994; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Academic Freedom: History (1), 1895-1961; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Academic Freedom: History (2), 1937-1956; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Academic Freedom: History (3), 1936-1971; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Academic Freedom: Profession and Law, 2002-2005; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Professors and Progressivism, undated; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - The Cold War and Academe, 1952-1986; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Salzberg Seminar, 1950s; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - "Crisis of Academic Authority"- Daedalus, 1969-1972; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Academic Freedom: Leftwing Critique, 1969-1988; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Academic Freedom: Rightwing Critique, 1985-1988; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Himstead File: Britton Corr, 1954-1961; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Metzger Correspondence: Himstead Interviews, 1960-1961; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Fuchs: Miscellaneous, 1956-1982; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Fuchs and Himstead, 1955-1985; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Committee O: Late Himstead, 1917-1956; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Special: William Fidler, March 14, 1958; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Himstead- Fuchs, 1985-1986; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Himstead- Miscellaneous, 1940-1966; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Himstead- Fuchs Notes, 1985; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Fuchs AAUP CORR, 1948-1955; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Institutional Autonomy, 1967-1987; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Menayd: "Future of Academic Freedom", 1992-1998; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Mobilization For Youth- Letter to Editor, 1964; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - "Origins of the Association" AAUP Bulletin, 1965; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Post Modernism and Academic Freedom, 1993; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Standing of US Universities in the World, 2003-2005; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - UCLA Law Review, 1963; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - "Student Freedom" in Order and Freedom- WCU, 1965; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - National Advisory Council on Academic Freedom, 1938-1939; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Student Freedom, March 1965; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Student Freedom, 1985; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Academic Freedom for Students (1), 1965-1981; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Academic Freedom for Students (2), 1963-1981; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - AAUP Tenure Studies, June 1979; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Tenure Statistics, 1995-1997; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Attacks on Tenure, 1977-1999; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Defense of Tenure, 1963-1993; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Tenure Article News, 1983-1997; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - History of Academic Tenure, undated; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Tenure Needed For Academic Freedom, undated; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Economics of Tenure, 1988; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Tenure and The Law, 1979-2000; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Where Tenure Does Not Exist, 1975-1982; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Tenure and Contracts, 1964-1975; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Definitions of Tenure, 1977; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Making Tenure Decisions, 1983-2003; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Associations in Higher Education and Tenure, 1964-1985; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Institutional Changes in Tenure Policies, 1972-1986; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Tenure Code- Columbia, 1971; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Twentieth Century Funds for Book on Tenure, 1986; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Tenure Clippings From Chronicles, 1976-1981; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - Tenure and Productivity, 1972-1993; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Tenure and the Law, 1790-1982; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Academic Tenure, 1910-1975; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Tenure and the Law, 1962-1977; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Academic Profession in Hard Times- Daedarus, 1974-1979; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - 1970 Interpretation of 1940 Statement, 1965-1969; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Conference Documents, 1938-1978; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Joint Committee Meeting on 1940 Statement of Principles on Academic Freedom and Tenure (1 of 2), February 26-27, 1969; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Joint Committee Meeting on 1940 Statement of Principles on Academic Freedom and Tenure (2 of 2), February 26-27, 1969; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Washington, 1949-1956; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - History of Childhood Quarterly: Journal of Psychohistory, 1974; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 17)
    - History of Childhood Quarterly: Journal of Psycohistory, 1975; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 17)
    - Journal of Air Law and Commerce, 1985; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 17)
    - Presidential Studies Quarterly, 1990; Series 2 Subseries 1 (Box 17)
  - Academic Freedom and Tenure Cases, 1889-1999; Series 2 Subseries 2
    This subseries contains AAUP and Committee A cases from various universities and subject matters concerning academic freedom in higher education within the United States. These files are dated from 1889-1999.
    - Academic Freedom- Bassett Case, 1903; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Various Cases, 1963-1995; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Various Cases, 1980-1999; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Cases of the Late 1950s (1 of 2), 1957-1959; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Cases of the Late 1950s (2 of 2), 1956-1959; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Committee A Published Cases- Academic Freedom, 1993; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Committee A: Black Colleges, 1959-1994; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - Committee A: CB Units, 1973-1979; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Cases: Classroom Behavior, 1964-1987; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Cases: Disciplinary Suspension, 1976; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Committee A Cases: Dismissal Due to Criticism of Administration, 1956-1991; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - Cases: Dismissal Prior to End of Term Appointment, 1980; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - Cases: Due Process, 1959-1975; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 19, Folder 8)
    - Committee A Cases: Excessive Probation, 1966-1986; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Committee A Cases: Extramural Freedom (Not Gripe), 1961-1989; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Cases: Late Notice, 1968-1980; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - AAUP Cases: Loyalty After 50s and 60s, 1963-1972; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Committee A: Memphis State College- Mason, 1954-1960; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Committee A: Michigan State College- Kneller, 1951-1955; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - Committee A Cases: No Tenure System, June 3, 1979; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - Committee A Cases: Ostensibly Financial (1 of 2), 1969-1992; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 20, Folder 8)
    - Committee A Cases: Ostensibly Financial (2 of 2), 1973-1997; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 20, Folder 9)
    - Cases: Personal Behavior, 1971-1979; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 20, Folder 10)
    - Cases: Research Personnel, 1967-1976; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - Cases: Student Disorders (1 of 2), 1970-1987; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - Cases: Student Disorders (2 of 2), 1961-1986; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - Cases: Tenure Pure and Simple, 1962-1990; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - Committee A: University of California Loyalty Oath, 1940-1955; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - Academic Freedom- Davidson, undated; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - Academic Freedom: Ely Case, 1894-1897; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - Expert Witness: Figueron- Rutgers, 1995-1996; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - Expert Witness: Franke, 1967-1997; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - Jeffries Case, 1992-1998; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - AAUP Policy: Levin Case, 1991-1992; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - Legislation: Senate Internal Security Subcommittee (Rutgers University), 1952-1953; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - Ross Case, 1901-1969; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - Texas Faculty Association: Expert Witness, 1971-1995; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - Special: University of California, 1949-1951; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - Warton- Nearing, 1915-1917; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - Cases, 1889-1984; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - Committee A Cases, 1929-1936; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - Knight Case, 1983-1984; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - AAUP Committees and Committee Policies, 1922-2009; Series 2 Subseries 3
    This subseries contains the papers of various committees and subcommittees within the American Association of University Professors and the policies they created for higher education institutions. These files are dated from 1922- 2009.
    - Kadish and Brown: Metzger on Review of Association Procedures, August 15, 1963; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - Metzger on Council, 1957-1973; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - Metzger on Council, 1980-1981; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - Metzger: Running For Vice President, 1975-1983; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 24, Folder 6)
    - My Comments to the Council, 1981-1997; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 24, Folder 7)
    - Metzger on Committee A, 1963-2003; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 24, Folder 8)
    - My Interventions into Cases: Not Expert Witness, 1959-1966; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - Subcommittee of A: My Services, 1972-1979; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - AAUP Policy: Utilities Invest, 1924-1925; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - AAUP Policy: Committee Z, 1949-1982; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - AAUP Policy: Merit Pay, 1973-1978; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - AAUP Policy: Moonlighting, 1967; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 25, Folder 6)
    - AAUP Policy: Judicial Notice Taken, 1968-1984; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 25, Folder 7)
    - AAUP Policy: Legal Interventions, 1949-1986; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 25, Folder 8)
    - Relationships with AFT, 1935-1939; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 25, Folder 9)
    - Relationship with American Federation of Teachers, 1939-1941; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 25, Folder 10)
    - AAUP Policy: Academic Freedom and Department Chairs, 1962-1994; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - AAUP Policy: Honorary Degrees, 1959-1986; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - AAUP Policy: Dismissal of Administrators, 1978; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - AAUP Policy: Appointments, 1967; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - AAUP Policy: Textbook Standardization, 1987; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - AAUP Policy: Changing Student Grades, undated; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - AAUP Policy: Critical Legal Studies and Academic Freedom, 1976-1988; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - AAUP Policy, 1996-1997; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 26, Folder 8)
    - AAUP Policy: Academic Freedom and Cyberspace, 1995-1997; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 26, Folder 9)
    - AAUP Policy: Copyright, 1998; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 26, Folder 10)
    - AAUP Policy: Extramural Utterance, 1963-1993; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 26, Folder 11)
    - AAUP Policy: Speaker Bans, 1965-1983; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 26, Folder 12)
    - AAUP Policy: Student Academic Freedom, 1960-2001; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 26, Folder 13)
    - AAUP Policy: Student Disruption, 1958-1980; Series 2 Subseries 2 (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - Student Freedom and Law, 1964-1986; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - AAUP Policy: Recourse to Lawyer in Academe, undated; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 27, Folder 3)
    - Committee A: Legal Liability of Faculty- Court Fees For Frivolous Suits, 1977-1986; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 27, Folder 4)
    - AAUP Policy: Court Costs as Deterrent to Suits That Fail, 1983-1986; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - AAUP Policy: Academic Freedom in Lower Schools, 1984-1986; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - AAUP Policy: Judicially- Compelled Discourse- Open Records, 1977-1995; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 27, Folder 7)
    - AAUP Policy: Access to Personnel Files, 1962-1996; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 27, Folder 8)
    - AAUP Policy: Sunshine Laws- Open Meetings, 1978-1986; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 27, Folder 9)
    - AAUP Policy: Buckley Amendment, 1974-1975; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - Furtive Surveillance, 1982-1995; Series 2 Subseries 3 (Box 28, Folder 2)